<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before his Maiestie at Oatelands, on the 28. of Iuly 1622. By Edmund Mason, his Maiesties chaplaine, and vicar of Nevvarke in Nottinghamshire</title>
            <author>Mason, Edmund, d. 1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07189</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112389</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847643</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12693</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07189)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12693)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1178:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before his Maiestie at Oatelands, on the 28. of Iuly 1622. By Edmund Mason, his Maiesties chaplaine, and vicar of Nevvarke in Nottinghamshire</title>
                  <author>Mason, Edmund, d. 1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXII. [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12693:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12693:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED before his MAIESTIE at <hi>Oatelands,</hi> on the 28. of Iuly 1622.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> EDMVND MASON, <hi>his Maieſties Chaplaine, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icar of</hi> NEVVARKE <hi>in Nottinghamſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> ¶ Printed by IOHN BILL. <hi>M.DC.XXII.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12693:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12693:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATTH. 16.21.</hi>
                  </bibl> The laſt words of the verſe are theſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>The Third Day.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the <hi>Garment</hi> of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">The Nature of the Text.</note> as well as his <hi>Body,</hi> ſo in the <hi>Hemme</hi> of Chriſts <hi>Garment,</hi> as well as the <hi>Garment,</hi> the woman with the bloody iſſue, Matth. 9.13. tells vs, there is <hi>ſauing vertue:</hi> both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and comfort for <hi>ſauing Faith,</hi> to <hi>touch</hi> and <hi>take,</hi> in the very <hi>Hemme.</hi> His <hi>Body</hi> wherein He wrought and ſuffered for vs, was that ſacred Perſon of the Diuine and Humane nature together, whereof wee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12693:3"/>are members and partakers, by the <hi>Touch</hi> of that Faith,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.5.</note> that Saint Paul ſayes, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues only, and captiuates Reaſon in obedient adoration.</hi> His <hi>Garments,</hi> wherein Hee was ſeene and knowne of vs, and for vs, were the workes and ſufferings of that moſt ſacred Perſon, <hi>His actiue and paſsiue obedience</hi> in our fleſh to the whole Law, wherewith our imperfect obedience is couered and accepted, by the <hi>Touch</hi> of that fayth, that S. Paul ſayes, does not beleeue only,
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>but workes through loue.</hi> Laſtly the <hi>Hemme</hi> of theſe <hi>Garments,</hi> wherwith the vnmeaſurable obedience, of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible Perſon, was cut out, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd, and confin'd to vs, and for vs; This was the needfull Circumſtances of <hi>Time, Place, Meanes, Manner,</hi> with other Virges, and Borders of His workes and ſufferings: in all which, as He ſhowd, He wrought as Man, and for man, and not as God onely; ſo in, and through them, the Circumſtances of our Actions, their <hi>times, place, meanes, manner,</hi> gather Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and acceptance, by the <hi>Touch</hi> of that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12693:3"/>Faith, which Saint Paul ſayes,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.6.</note> does not onely beleeue and worke, but <hi>is the meaſure and proportion of our Actions</hi> to His. Rom. 12.6.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Garments</hi> of Chriſts workes, muſt be <hi>hem'd</hi> in with Circumſtances, or elſe they cannot bee ſutable to vs, nor for vs. <hi>Ours</hi> they cannot be, vnleſſe they be of our Faſhion. No more then himſelfe can bee <hi>Ours,</hi> vnleſſe He take our Forme. And yet the faſhion onely, does not make them <hi>Ours:</hi> we muſt <hi>touch</hi> a'm too, take hold of a'm, and put a'm on. And that wee may do ſo, the <hi>Summe of ſauing Faith,</hi> our Creed tels vs, our Faith muſt <hi>touch</hi> &amp; gather ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, from the <hi>Hemme,</hi> as well as the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> the Circumſtance, as well as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, the manner, as well as the worke, that Chriſt did for vs.</p>
            <p>It is not enough to beleeue He was <hi>borne</hi> in our fleſh, vnleſſe we beleeue the <hi>meanes</hi> too, of a Virgin, and the Virgin Mary too: No benefit nor comfort elſe. It is not enough to beleeue He <hi>ſuffered</hi> for vs, vnleſſe both the manner, <hi>Crucified,</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12693:4"/>meanes, <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> the intent, <hi>Dead;</hi> the extent, <hi>Buried;</hi> vnleſſe all theſe bee <hi>touched,</hi> faith gathers no vertue. It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beleeue, He <hi>deſcended,</hi> vnleſſe our Faith reach to the very circumſtance of place, <hi>into Hell.</hi> It is not enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue He <hi>Roſe againe,</hi> vnleſſe our Faith <hi>touch,</hi> and gather vertue from the very <hi>Hemme</hi> and circumſtance of time, <hi>The Third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So we might go on,
<note place="margin">The ſcope of it.</note> till He come againe to Iudgement, at the <hi>laſt Day:</hi> But heere the <hi>Third Day</hi> ſtayes vs. And this <hi>Hemme</hi> of time, requires our <hi>Touch,</hi> and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, not of the worke of the day, and the benefit of it; for it is not Eaſter now; but only of the day of the worke, and the benefit of it, <hi>the Third Day;</hi> for it is the Lords <hi>Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And a <hi>Hemme</hi> it is, and no better: an hiſtoricall and drie circumſtance of time onely. But it is in our Creed, and that <hi>touches</hi> vs neerely. And in all our Creed, it is the only circumſtance of Time there mention'd. Doubtleſſe there is ſome
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12693:4"/>
               <hi>Redemption</hi> in it. With the woman with the bloody iſſue, let vs but <hi>touch</hi> it a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; there may chance come that vertue from it, that may <hi>redimere tempus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.16.</note> as Saint Paul ſayes: at leaſt ſhow, the <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Time,</hi> and turne the vanity, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xation of the <hi>Dayes</hi> of Earth, into the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty and Comfort of the <hi>Dayes</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. For that's the purpoſe of the Text.</p>
            <p>And according to that purpoſe,
<note place="margin">The Diuiſion</note> Let vs diuide our diſcourſe into a twofold <hi>touch,</hi> and conſideration. One, of Hiſtoricall faith, the ſpirituall mans left hand, <hi>tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> the <hi>Hemme</hi> of Time only, that <hi>Christ did riſe vpon a Third Day.</hi> Another of Iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying, and ſauing faith, the ſpirituall mans right hand, <hi>Touching</hi> the vertue of this <hi>Hemme,</hi> that, <hi>For vs it was Neceſſary, that Chriſt ſhould riſe vpon a Third Day, and no other.</hi> The <hi>Hemme</hi> I will <hi>touch</hi> in a word; the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue,</hi> by your patience, I will <hi>handle,</hi> but not in many words: the Diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">The <hi>First Touch</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Third day.</hi>
               </note> and the Text ſhall be ſhort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. And</p>
            <p>Touching the <hi>Hemme</hi> of time firſt, It
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12693:5"/>is <hi>touched</hi> a little too much. <hi>Touched</hi> it is, as God would not haue his Annoynted <hi>touched. Angunt dum tangunt.</hi> As the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude <hi>touch'd</hi> Chriſt in Iayrus houſe, when the woman with the bloody iſſue <hi>touch'd</hi> him too. But in their <hi>touching, Confligunt &amp; afflictant,</hi> ſayes Saint Peter: In ſtead of gathering vertue from him, they throng, and preſſe him, moleſt, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict him with their <hi>Touching:</hi> And ſo the old aduerſary of Faith, the Deuill, he has taught many to <hi>touch</hi> this circumſtance. Where hee cannot hinder the <hi>Touch</hi> of Knowledge, yet to corrupt, or hinder the <hi>Touch</hi> of Faith, he has taught a'm to preſſe it with doubts, afflict it with queſtions,
<q>Diſputare malle quam viuere:</q> To diſpute with it, to doe any thing to it, rather then beleeue, and be whole. Some diſpute the Integrity of three dayes. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers call the <hi>Houres</hi> to account, and in their Auditt finde not aboue forty. And yet let either of theſe bee <hi>touch'd</hi> with a Tertian Ague, they will confidently ſay, their fit return'd <hi>the third day,</hi> when it is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12693:5"/>not yet aboue forty <hi>houres,</hi> ſince the fit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted. A Feuer it is, and an euill ſpirit that vexes theſe diſputers: For the ſtory in the Goſpel is cleere enough in ſhort. Take we the Iewes reckoning of time, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Gods meaſure of a Day in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.5.</note> from the beginning of the euening, till the euening return'd againe; and then it is plaine enough, that vpon the day of the Iewes <hi>Preparation,</hi> whereon Chriſt ſuffred, Hee was both <hi>dead,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scriptures,
<note place="margin">Math. 27.46. Mar. 15.42. Luc. 23.54.</note> and as ſome ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>buryed</hi> by Ioſeph and Nicodemus, <hi>three houres</hi> before Sun-ſet, and that is <hi>one day.</hi> For I preach to day, though I preach not all the day. Then all the euening and morning, the whole day of the <hi>Iewes Sabbath,</hi> He lay in his graue, and that's <hi>another day.</hi> Then all the euening quite through, vntill the morning, of the firſt Day of the weeke,
<note place="margin">Math. 27.66.</note> He was <hi>ſealed</hi> in His Sepulchre; And that's <hi>the third day,</hi> wherein Hee <hi>roſe</hi> gloriouſly from the Dead, and fully accompliſhed our Iuſtification againſt the ſting of
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.25.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:12693:6"/>Death, our <hi>Sinne,</hi> the ſtrength of ſinne the <hi>Law,</hi> the victory of Hell, our <hi>Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation;</hi> Ouer all which, there was <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, Triumph,</hi> and <hi>perpetuall Dominion</hi> both taken in, and giuen to our fleſh, by that his Reſurrection, <hi>the third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by that his Reſurrection onely, I doe not ſay; but I adde too, as a maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece in this great Building, by that his Reſurrection, <hi>The third Day.</hi> Together they went, and together Faith muſt <hi>touch</hi> a'm, as the woman <hi>touch'd</hi> the <hi>Hemme,</hi> and the <hi>Garment</hi> together. <hi>The third Day</hi> is a prop and ſtay to Faith, as well as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection. For to keepe my word;</p>
            <p>Let vs leaue now the <hi>Left hand touch</hi> of Hiſtoricall faith, That ſuch a thing, was ſo done, by ſuch a Perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, at ſuch a time; which the Deuil, that teaches others to diſput, yet himſelfe beleeues; &amp; conuicted in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, trembles at the very <hi>Hemme</hi> of time;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Second Touch,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the <hi>third day.</hi>
               </note> And come to the <hi>Right hand touch</hi> of Iuſtifying and ſauing Faith, That ſuch a thing was ſo done, by ſuch a Perſon, at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12693:6"/>ſuch a time, for me, and you, and the whole world, to <hi>iuſtifie our conquering ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to God, with full power of the Sonnes of God; to doe all good, and reſist all euill, either to be done, or ſuffred:</hi> This vertue and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Chriſts Reſurrection, Faith can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not draw from it, to the ſoules reſt, and ſtay of the mind, vnleſſe the aſſent of Faith to Chriſts Reſurrection, be ſtayd, and determin'd vpon the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very <hi>third Day,</hi> it was done in, and no other. Neither the <hi>firſt Day,</hi> wherein he ſuffred, Nor the <hi>ſecond Day,</hi> the Iewes Sabbath, Nor any Day beyond <hi>the third Day.</hi> That Chriſt may reſolue my Faith, that he is the Chriſt, and roſe againe for me, He muſt not only riſe, but riſe <hi>the third Day,</hi> and no other.</p>
            <p>And, to Diſcouer this Myſtery of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, As theſe Dayes of Chriſt are <hi>three;</hi> So I find accordingly, <hi>three ſeuerall Dayes</hi> of the Church and myſticall body of Chriſt, as alſo three ſeuerall Diuinities, and Lights of <hi>theſe three Dayes,</hi> all inligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tening the neceſſity of <hi>this Third Day.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12693:7"/>The firſt is the Diuinity of the <hi>Primitiue Day,</hi> the <hi>Good Friday</hi> of the Church, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt was perſecuted, and ſuffred in his Members, &amp; myſticall body, through Heatheniſme and Hereſie; The light of which day, was <hi>ſimplicity of Faith vnto ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Diuinity of the <hi>Schoole Day,</hi> what we cal the <hi>Popiſh Day,</hi> the Iewes Sabbath of the Church, wherein the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body of Ieſus Chriſt lay <hi>wrapped</hi> in the Linnens of Iewiſh Ceremonies, &amp; <hi>bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed</hi> in the New-found Sepulchre of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane inuentions; the light of which day, was <hi>Subtilty of Reaſonings;</hi> &amp;, where there was not more Miſt then Sun-ſhine, <hi>vnto ſaluation</hi> too.</p>
            <p>The third is the Diuinity of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Day,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection Day</hi> of the Church, when after a darke euening, and a little cloudy dawning of trouble, and perſecution in the beginning of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Sun of Righteouſnes roſe glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in our Hemiſphere, enlighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing our woſterne world, with the <hi>ſimple ſubtilty</hi> of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12693:7"/>Saint Pauls <hi>fooliſh wiſedome vnto ſaluation,</hi> call'd, <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe Dayes gaue their ſeuerall lights to this point in hand, and from the ſame Sunne of Righteouſnes, though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with equall force, nor in the ſame meaſure. The firſt ſhewes the Neceſſity of the <hi>third Day,</hi> in reſpect of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in whoſe Name Chriſt roſe, that is <hi>Adam.</hi> The ſecond, in reſpect of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherin Chriſt Roſe, that is <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi> The third, in reſpect of the Perſons to whom, and for whom he roſe, that is, Iewes and Gentiles, <hi>the ſonnes of Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let me light a'm vp all,
<note place="margin">The Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Third Day</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Perſon, in whoſe Name Chriſt roſe.</note> and as our Sauiour wills, let me ſet, a'm vpon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and in their own order and diſcourſe: Firſt the ſimple Faith of the Primitiue Church, both <hi>touch'd</hi> the Neceſſity, and drew foorth the Benefit of <hi>the Third Day,</hi> vpon the plaineſt grounds, that are lai'd, and lai'd open in holy Scripture;
<note place="margin">Tertul. aduer. Iud. cap. 13. Athan. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car. verbi Chryſoſtome Hom. 89. in Mat.</note> and yet not allneither. Tertullian, Athanaſius, and Chryſoſtome, to take the marrow of their ſimple meaning, all pitch their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12693:8"/>vpon <hi>theſe two</hi> eſpecially. No dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the riſing beyong <hi>the third Day,</hi> ſay they; Partly for the <hi>Comfort</hi> of his friends, that expected it ſhould be <hi>then,</hi> Partly for the <hi>Conuiction</hi> of his enemies, that endeuour'd it ſhould not bee <hi>then.</hi> Had he riſen any day, but the promiſed <hi>third Day,</hi> all his Diſciples and friends would haue turn'd Thomaſes, and, as he did, haue requir'd another <hi>Touch</hi> and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring of him, ere they would haue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and taken Comfort.
<note place="margin">Mat. 27.62.63</note> And had he not riſen vpon the appointed <hi>third Day,</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till which <hi>Day</hi> the ſouldiers were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by the Prieſts <hi>intreaty,</hi> and Pilates <hi>charge,</hi> to watch the Sepulchre, with the ſeale vpon it, to make all ſure, for feare, forſooth, his moſt fearful Diſciples ſhould ſteale him away, who were ready, God wot, to ſteale themſelues away, out of all ſight) Had he not then riſen in the preſence and ſight of the very ſouldiers, the ſouldiers had not <hi>testified</hi> his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to his enemies as they did, Matt. 28.11.
<note place="margin">Mat. 28.11.</note> His enemies had not beene <hi>conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12693:8"/>by the Teſtimony,
<note place="margin">Matt. 28.12.</note> as they were and ſhew'd it, by corrupting the ſouldiers to conceale the truth. For that corruption to conceale, was a plaine confeſſion, that they were indeed, onely they would not ſeeme to be conuicted, and taken in their owne ſnare.</p>
            <p>The ſpite of His enemies, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in them, was at the <hi>third Day</hi> onely. The comfort of his friends, and ſimple faith in them, was in the <hi>third Day</hi> onely. It was the <hi>third Day</hi> onely, that could <hi>conuince</hi> the one, and <hi>comfort</hi> the other; and it did both. But why, I beſeech you? and what was this conuiction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of this <hi>third Day?</hi> Was it the bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of the naturall body to life againe the <hi>third Day,</hi> that malicious feare would haue hindered?
<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.47.</note> The Diuell indeed was angrie when Lazarus was rays'd to life: or was it the bare fruition of his bodily pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and company againe the <hi>third Day,</hi> that ſimple fayth expected <hi>comfort</hi> in? There was comfort indeed in this:
<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.45.</note> and both comfort, and fayth, followed Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12693:9"/>rayſing: But this is not comfort of <hi>ſimple,</hi> but of <hi>ſenſuall</hi> Faith. In this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that is beleeued, becauſe it is <hi>ſeene</hi> or <hi>felt;</hi> there is a <hi>mixture</hi> of fleſh, a <hi>compoſition</hi> of ſenſuall delight, from which the <hi>Touch of ſimple faith</hi> is moſt pure and free.</p>
            <p>For <hi>ſimple Faith</hi> is an <hi>euidence of things vnſeene,</hi> ſayes S. Paul, Heb. 11.1. And our Sauiour tels Thomas, that, <hi>Beatifica fides, The bleſſed, or bleſsing faith, is that, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſees nor feeles, and yet then beleeues moſt:</hi> It vſes no helpe of fence, but the fence of hearing only:
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> It comes by <hi>hearing</hi> only, and what it heares was foreſhewne in the <hi>typicall body,</hi> and done and perform'd in the <hi>Naturall and reall body</hi> of Chriſt Ieſus, that it verily beleeues, is communicated to His <hi>Mysticall body:</hi> And what it ſo heares, and beleeues, it <hi>beleeues euidently,</hi> though it ſee it not; It <hi>tasts really,</hi> though it chew it not; It <hi>feeles and enioyes ſubſtantially,</hi> though it touch it not, nor finger it, or els it is not <hi>ſimple,</hi> but <hi>ſenſuall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another comfort therefore wee muſt finde for <hi>ſimple Faith</hi> in the <hi>third Day.</hi> And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12693:9"/>S. Chryſoſtome giues it: The comfort,
<note place="margin">Loco ſup.</note> ſayth he, that <hi>ſimple Faith</hi> in his friends ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and Deuilliſh malice in his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies would haue hindered, it was that <hi>vnſeene comfort,</hi> that S. Paul ſpeakes of, 1. Cor. 15.20.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.20.</note> That Chriſt riſing <hi>the third day,</hi> was manifeſted to be <hi>Primitiae dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium; The firſt fruits</hi> of them that ſleepe in hope of Reſurrection to life. This was the comfort <hi>ſimple faith</hi> look't at, and the Deuill had good cauſe not to abide. He, the <hi>firſt fruites</hi> of the myſticall body, and therefore as He, ſo all the reſt, of his kinde and generation, with Him. And He therefore the <hi>firſt fruites,</hi> and no other, that was rayſed from the dead, becauſe He only, and no other was rays'd <hi>the third day.</hi> Heere was the cauſe of the Deuils watch and ſeale. Iayrus daughter was rays'd, but vpon the <hi>first day.</hi> The widowes ſonne was rays'd, but vpon the <hi>ſecond day,</hi> the buriall day. Lazarus was rays'd, but vpon the <hi>fourth day.</hi> The Deuill neither watch'd theſe, nor ſeal'd their graues. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Chriſt, was rays'd the <hi>third day:</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12693:10"/>therefore Hee onely, and no other, the <hi>terrible and comfortable firſt fruites,</hi> of them that ſleepe.</p>
            <p>Doe you queſtion the reaſon yet, and thinke the argument weake? Ile reſolue you in a word.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in the Legall and Typicall firſt fruites, though we finde no expreſſe Law, neceſſity, nor mention of the <hi>third day</hi> for their offering; Yet this Law we read Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. 23.15.
<note place="margin">Leuit. 23.15.</note> and a ſtatute for euer, that the <hi>ſheafe of the fruites to be accepted for them, was to be wau'd before the Lord, the morrow after the Sabbath, ſeuen Sabbaths complete, before the feaſt of Pentecoſt.</hi> And this morrow, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Sabbath, was iuſt <hi>this third day</hi> and houre, when Chriſt only, &amp; no other was wau'd and lifted vp from the dead, the <hi>first fruits</hi> of all his kinde. So the type is ſure for vs, that He was onely the prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> becauſe Hee onely was rays'd vpon this morrow.</p>
            <p>But if this will not ſerue, In this Euangelicall and ſubſtantiall <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> we finde an expreſſe neceſſity of <hi>this third day,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:12693:10"/>according to Gods Oeconomy, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of grace vnto vs.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.21.22.</note> And S. Paul tenders it in the place before nam'd. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God of his meere mercy, purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to recouer mankinde, from vnder the curſe of death, ſo ſweetly diſpoſed of it, that, <hi>as by man came death, ſo by man alſo ſhould come the Reſurrection from the dead. As</hi> by the firſt Adam, whoſe fleſh and bloud we are by generation, <hi>Death; So</hi> by the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adam, whoſe fleſh and bone we are by Regeneration, <hi>Reſurrection to life. As,</hi> and <hi>So;</hi> in due proportion and reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance. As therefore in the firſt Adam, <hi>the firſt fruites of all liuing</hi> to the world, all die, and from him <hi>Eccleſia morientium,</hi> a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of fallers into death, were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; ſo in the ſecond Adam, Chriſt, <hi>the first fruites of all that die</hi> to the world, all are made aliue, and from him <hi>Eccleſia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgentium,</hi> a congregation of riſers to God were gather'd. As Adams congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was gather'd by a riſing, to fall, from life vnto death; ſo Chriſts congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was gather'd by a falling, to riſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12693:11"/>from death vnto life. As Adam roſe, and fell, and gathered his congregation, the <hi>third day</hi> after life; ſo Chriſt roſe, and ſtood, and gathered his congregation the <hi>third day</hi> after death. And heere is Saint Pauls <hi>As,</hi> and <hi>So.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The full proportion, betweene the two Adams, whereupon ſimple Faith in <hi>hearing,</hi> both determines her <hi>aſſent,</hi> and to the <hi>conuiction</hi> of all malice, gathers this <hi>comfort,</hi> that Chriſt was indeede the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in whoſe name He came, Her ſecond Adam,</hi> her firſt fruites, her perfect patterne and ſamplar of her nature, eſtate, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that He onely, and no other, was rayſed the <hi>third day, and no other.</hi> And this was Primitiue Diuinity, what S. Paul cals the <hi>chaſte virgin, ſimplicity in Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 2.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11 3.</note> Cor. 11.3.</p>
            <p>Nor in the ſecond place,
<note place="margin">The neceſſity of the third Day in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Perſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Chriſt roſe.</note> does the <hi>ſchoole ſubtilty</hi> at all corrupt this <hi>virgin ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity,</hi> or obſcure this light, with any forc'd or falſe gloſſes: It rather inlightens it more, bringing more inſtruction with comfort to the <hi>touch of Faith,</hi> in reſpect of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12693:11"/>the <hi>Perſon wherein Christ</hi> roſe. And thus they reaſon, the third day to Faiths, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 14 to 20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt certaine it is, as Saint Paul ſayes, 1. Cor. 15. that were it not for the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the dead, there is nothing ſo vaine, as the <hi>aſſurance,</hi> nothing ſo miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as the <hi>preaching,</hi> and preachers of Chriſt Ieſus. It is onely the hope of the reſurrection, that makes you ſerue Chriſt, and vs ſerue you. Now to hope for this, it is fit we be fully inſtructed in it, and to be inſtructed in it fully, wee muſt firſt bee fully aſſured, both of his <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> that ſhould riſe, but alone could not, and of his <hi>Diuine Nature,</hi> that could not but riſe, but alone would not without the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. For to beleeue our reſurrection, we muſt firſt beleeue our ſelues to bee parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of <hi>both theſe Natures:</hi> Of both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or elſe no reſurrection. The <hi>Diuine</hi> without the <hi>Humane</hi> needs not, the <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> without the <hi>Diuine</hi> cannot. And to beleeue our ſelues partaker of both theſe, our faith muſt firſt be confirmed, in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12693:12"/>truth of them both, in our <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> our <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> with whoſe entire nature we participate by <hi>reſurrection,</hi> as with the firſt by <hi>generation.</hi> Hee muſt haue both, or we cannot; if He haue both, we want neither. To confirme therfore our faith in the truth of Chriſts <hi>Diuine Nature,</hi> that would die, but ſhould not, it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary He ſhould riſe <hi>ſoone.</hi> To confirme our faith in the truth of his <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that ſhould riſe, but alone could not, it was neceſſary He ſhould not riſe <hi>too ſoon</hi> And this <hi>ſoone</hi> for his <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and not <hi>too ſoone</hi> for his <hi>Humanity,</hi> was <hi>the third Day</hi> onely. <hi>Soone,</hi> ſayes his <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and not beyond <hi>the third Day;</hi> not <hi>too ſoone,</hi> ſaies his <hi>Humanity,</hi> &amp; not before <hi>the third Day.</hi> haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his reſurrection vpon <hi>the third Day,</hi> it appear'd manifeſtly, there was ſomthing in his fleſh, and that bodily, that death might <hi>ſwallow</hi> with the fleſh, as a fiſh doth a hooke, or a Hawke caſting: but death could not <hi>hold it,</hi> not digeſt it, not conuert it into her ſubſtance of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and putrefaction, which begins <hi>the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12693:12"/>third Day,</hi> and eſpecially in a wounded body.</p>
            <p>She had ſnatch'd Chriſts body greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the Croſſe; But when ſhee came to endew it, put it ouer, and conuert it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her ſubſtance of corruption, at her due time, <hi>the third Day,</hi> it would not doe; ſhee could not chuſe but reſtore him, and with him all, that by faith in him had any part of the Diuine Nature. Could that holy one haue ſeene, much leſſe feele any corruption, the Diuine nature, that dwelt in him bodily, had not beene there. But <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes Saint Peter, Act. 2.24.
<note place="margin">Act. 2.24.</note> It was not <hi>poſsible that ſuch a Perſon ſhould be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the paines of death.</hi> Of Death, Hee might be, and was for a while; true fleſh requir'd it, true God will'd it: But of the paines and penalties of Death, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and putrefaction <hi>of the third Day,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it was impoſſible that Diuinitie ſhould be held by a'm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So long</hi> it was poſſible, but <hi>no longer,</hi> and as <hi>ſo long,</hi> and <hi>no longer,</hi> was neceſſary to ſhew Diuinity was there; ſo, <hi>ſo long,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12693:13"/>
               <hi>no ſooner,</hi> was neceſſary to ſhew Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was there too. A pawſe did well for that. The firſt or ſecond day had beene too haſty: Hee would not elſe haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd Man, and ſomething that might die: His death would haue beene ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a ſwound, a fit of an Apoplexie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps but fayn'd, and ſo all faith vaine, and hope comfortleſſe. Till <hi>the third Day</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſtayes, becauſe ſo long to ſtay, as it was neceſſary to ſhew his mortall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo it was ſufficient to ſhew it. For in leſſe then that time, by many howres, no man ſeemes dead, and is aliue, but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhewes ſome tokens of life, or dies out right. So that in a word, To ſtay <hi>ſo long as the third Day,</hi> was neceſſary to ſhew his <hi>Humanity,</hi> which ſhould not riſe any ſooner, and it did ſhew it; To ſtay <hi>no longer then the third Day,</hi> was neceſſary to ſhew his <hi>Diuinity,</hi> which might ſtay no longer, and it did ſhew it. It was the <hi>third Day</hi> onely, that could giue faith <hi>aſſurance,</hi> her head, and firſt fruits was <hi>ſuch a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and roſe in both the Natures of God and man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:12693:13"/>
            <p>Nor is it <hi>aſsurance</hi> only, but <hi>Comfort</hi> too, ſaies the ſchoole; for in that this <hi>Diuine</hi> &amp; <hi>Humane Nature</hi> ſtay'd thus in the graue, <hi>two whole nights, and one whole day,</hi> it is our conſolation, ſaith Thomas,
<note place="margin">Thom. Aqu. q. 53. ar. 2. con.</note> that Chriſt by his owne <hi>bodily death</hi> which in him was all <hi>light,</hi> through the righteouſneſſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence of his fleſh, has fully deſtroyd <hi>our two deaths,</hi> both of ſoule and body, which in vs, are all <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> through ſinne.
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ero mors tua O mors,</hi> O death I will be thy death, was fulfill'd in theſe <hi>two nights. Death</hi> is now dead, and has no more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer ouer vs, then it had ouer Him; but in our <hi>death</hi> now, wee are conformable and ſubiect to him onely. Our <hi>head ſtay'd</hi> a while in <hi>death,</hi> but was not <hi>detain'd</hi> by <hi>death:</hi> as long as He thought it conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for our beliefe of His <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> ſo long He ſtay'd: when He thought it conuenient for our beliefe of His <hi>Diuine Nature,</hi> He roſe againe: He both <hi>ſtay'd</hi> &amp; <hi>roſe</hi> at his owne will, hauing ſlaine death with the <hi>Diuine Nature,</hi> for ſeazing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly vpon the innocent <hi>Humane Nature.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:12693:14"/>To ſhew that iuſt ſo the members parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king with that <hi>Head, conformable</hi> in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, though not <hi>equall</hi> in vertue and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, no more then my toe is to my head; yet iuſt ſo they die, and iuſt ſo they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in <hi>death.</hi> In <hi>death</hi> they are detain'd, but not by death at all, or any power of hers, but onely by the will of Chriſt their head; ſo long as he pleaſes, they ſhall reſt in hope, and no longer.</p>
            <p>Before he was our <hi>head</hi> in time, which was at <hi>the third Day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1.20.22.</note> Eph. 1.20, 22. Death was a darkeneſſe, and a deepe priſon; and that, to them that died in the hope of his firſt comming. But ſince hee is riſen <hi>the third Day,</hi> and hath taken away the <hi>darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our two nights,</hi> the <hi>darkeneſſe of death</hi> is taken away.
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>Mori mihi lucrum,</hi> to die is gaine; to be in her priſon, is to bee in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; to be detain'd in death, is to bee in light and life. But to whom? To thoſe onely that communicate with that <hi>Head,</hi> that roſe <hi>the third Day;</hi> becauſe hee was God, and could haue <hi>riſen ſooner,</hi> and yet roſe <hi>no ſooner</hi> then <hi>the third Day;</hi> becauſe he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12693:14"/>was man, and would ſhew that man has now power, as to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> ſo to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of death, and as in <hi>himſelfe,</hi> ſo in all his <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus far the light of <hi>ſchoole ſubtilty</hi> leads vs, to the <hi>vertue of this Hemme,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Perſon wherein Chriſt roſe:</hi> It prooues his <hi>Diuine Nature,</hi> his <hi>Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> his <hi>power ouer death,</hi> our <hi>liberty in death,</hi> at his diſpoſe onely, and not at deaths at all, and ſo before wee are aware,
<note place="margin">The neceſſity of <hi>the third Day</hi> in reſpect of the perſons to whom and for whom Chriſt roſe.</note> wee are gotten into the third reſpect, <hi>To our ſelues, and thoſe perſons, to whom, and for whom hee roſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wee are but entred only: to ſhew it more fully, the <hi>light of reformed wiſedome</hi> remaines now, which, as in this point, it neither oppoſes, nor departs from, either primitiue ſubtilty, or ſchoole ſubtilty: ſo it is a <hi>third witneſse,</hi> to eſtabliſh the vertue of this <hi>third Day,</hi> &amp; all together will make vp the wiſe mans triple twiſted cord that cannot eaſily bee broken.</p>
            <p>Our firſt reaſon of the <hi>third Day</hi> (for I muſt make haſte, as in all points elſe) is,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12693:15"/>that the <hi>Scriptures might bee fulfill'd, and the word of God be cleare in our eyes and hearts:</hi> nor is it ours firſt, but S. Pauls firſt, 1. Cor. 15.4.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>And that hee roſe againe the third Day, according to the Scriptures.</hi> And when S. Paul names Scriptures, as when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour names a'm, hee meanes either the <hi>propheſies of the third Day,</hi> or the <hi>types and figures of the third Day,</hi> or both together; and both together, I beleeue, he meanes; for both there were of it, and according to both; and to fulfill both, Chriſt roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>the third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The propheſie we find,
<note place="margin">This prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by S. Paul Eph. 2.5.6. which with the whole paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to cut of for Breuity. <hi>verba Pauli Conuiuificauit Conreſuſcitauit.</hi> Tertul. loc. ſup.</note> Oſee. 6.2. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter two daies he will reuiue vs, in <hi>the third Day</hi> he will raiſe vs vp, and we ſhall liue in his ſight: It is not <hi>him</hi> only, but <hi>vs;</hi> and for vs ſure, and not for <hi>himſelfe</hi> only, both the Prophet beſpoke it, and Chriſt did it. And as it is ſpoken of the long expected Meſſias; ſo Tertul. vrges it ſo ſtrongly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Iewes, as if Chriſt had riſen on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>the third Day,</hi> to fulfill this propheſie, and remember the Iewes of it.</p>
            <p>The reuiuing, the raiſing, the life, the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12693:15"/>benefit, the whole propheſie, they ſaw all fulfilled to the <hi>very expected houre,</hi> and by <hi>none elſe,</hi> but by Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and at <hi>no time elſe,</hi> but the <hi>third Day</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. They fulfil'd the prophecies, in killing their Meſſias, but would not beleeue their Meſſias, in fulfilling the prophecies. But, as the faſhion is, they <hi>kill'd</hi> the Prophets, and <hi>buried</hi> all the prophecies. And let vs let the prophecie paſſe, and periſh with our Sermons, and make nothing of it, as the Iewes did.</p>
            <p>That they could <hi>forget</hi> a <hi>prophecy,</hi> when they could <hi>kill a Prophet,</hi> it is ſo ordinary amongſt vs, as it is no wonder in them. But yet their <hi>beloued remembrancers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22.</note> whom S. Paul ſayes they lou'd aboue all things, that is, Types, ſignes, and figures, as they could not kill a'm, ſo it was very ſtrange they could not remember a'm, and this <hi>third Day</hi> put a'm in minde of.</p>
            <p>Amongſt many other, had they but remembred either <hi>Iſaac</hi> among their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or <hi>Ioſeph</hi> amongſt their brethren, or <hi>Ionas</hi> amongſt their miniſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12693:16"/>this very <hi>third Day</hi> had beene argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment enough, that the Riſer the <hi>third Day</hi> was their <hi>full Meſsias,</hi> both <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet.</hi> Both their <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> to ſacrifice, and be ſacrificed for them: their <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>King</hi> to feed, ſaue, and comfort them: and their <hi>Ionas</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> to teach and inſtruct a'm in the right way, and all becauſe He roſe <hi>the third Day.</hi> Firſt <hi>Iſaac</hi> going with his father to bee ſacrificed for him,
<note place="margin">Gen. 22.4.</note> Gen. 22.4. Vntill the <hi>third Day,</hi> hee was no better then a dead man, neither in his fathers opinion, nor his owne condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But the <hi>third Day</hi> he was reuiu'd and rays'd againe from the dead, and made the firſt fruits of the bleſſed ſeed,
<note place="margin">16.18.</note> at the 18. verſ. Then <hi>Ioſeph</hi> vntill the <hi>third yeere,</hi> was a poore priſoner in the ſtocks,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.18.</note> the iron en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into his ſoule: But in the <hi>third yeere,</hi> he was deliuered, and made the gouernor and commander of all Egypt,
<note place="margin">Gen. 41.1.</note> Gen. 41.1. Laſtly, <hi>Ionas,</hi> for <hi>three dayes</hi> was in the Whales belly,
<note place="margin">Ion. 2.10.</note> and what better then dead? But then the fiſh could not hold him, but caſt him vp on the dry land, and hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12693:16"/>the great Prophet of the Gentiles, and Preacher of Repentance to them.</p>
            <p>Now all theſe foretold Chriſt, or who but He? The Iew will not name another; and all this Chriſt only fulfilled, or who but He? Can the Iew tell vs? And when did Hee fulfill all this, but vpon <hi>the third Day?</hi> But the Iewe will not beleeue it. What <hi>vertue</hi> therefore the Iewes would not gather out of this <hi>Hemme,</hi> let it flow vnto vs of the Gentiles, to whom the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and the <hi>Hemme</hi> reaches. That Chriſt riſing the <hi>third Day,</hi> according to theſe Scriptures; it is Chriſt, and none elſe, that is our <hi>Iſaac,</hi> both our <hi>ſacrifice</hi> for ſin, and yet our <hi>first fruits</hi> of the bleſſed ſeed. It is Chriſt, and none elſe, that is our <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> both the <hi>bond-ſeruant</hi> that was ſold by vs, and for vs, and yet our <hi>only Lord</hi> and relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in all want. It is Chriſt, and none elſe, that is our <hi>Ionas,</hi> both our <hi>pledge</hi> puniſhed for vs, and yet our <hi>preacher</hi> of amendment to ſafety. The <hi>ſacrifice</hi> in feare, the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of hope, the <hi>freedome</hi> in bondage, the <hi>ſuccour</hi> in want, the <hi>pledge</hi> in danger, the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12693:17"/>
               <hi>guide</hi> in errour: all this Chriſt is, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is, becauſe it pleaſed him to riſe our <hi>Iſaac,</hi> our <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> our <hi>Ionas,</hi> our <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> our <hi>full Meſsias</hi> according to the Scriptures, the <hi>third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus Hee fulfill'd His Fathers <hi>word,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in being rais'd the <hi>third Day,</hi> according to that <hi>word;</hi> and for that, faith is embolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to take His fathers <hi>word,</hi> and giue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to his bare <hi>word.</hi> And next to His fathers <hi>word,</hi> which is our next reaſon, to <hi>fulfill his owne word and prediction of Himſelfe,</hi> and purchaſe faith to it too, He <hi>kept the day</hi> too.
<note place="margin">Athan. loc. ſup.</note> This was Athanaſius reaſon before vs, but we make it <hi>fuller,</hi> and finde more <hi>vertue</hi> in it. He roſe the <hi>third Day,</hi> becauſe He had ſayd, He would; and my <hi>text</hi> is the firſt word, that ere He gaue for it: and therefore Hee will keepe his word with vs, whatſoeuer Hee has promis'd. This was Athanaſius reaſon and comfort, <hi>Hee is a man of his word.</hi> And t'is much this, but t'is not enough. He had ſayd, He would riſe the <hi>third day,</hi> and He did ſo, and Hee put it into my Creed; and in all my Creed
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12693:17"/>there is no circumſtance of time but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this: therefore He will not onely <hi>keepe His word with vs,</hi> as well as Gods; but He will <hi>keepe His time with vs</hi> to a minute. He will not onely pay the <hi>full ſumme</hi> Hee has promis'd, but Hee will pay it at <hi>the day;</hi> He will not breake an hower. This is the comfort and vertue that faith ſuckes from the <hi>third Day,</hi> and from no particle in the Creed beſides.</p>
            <p>When the Angels at the Sepulchre, Luc. 24.6. ſayd to the women, <hi>Why ſeeke yee the liuing amongst the dead? He is not heere, but is riſen;</hi> He addes too; <hi>Remember, how hee spake vnto you, when he was yet in Galilee, ſaying. The Sonne of man muſt be deliuered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of ſinfull men, and be crucified, and the third Day riſe againe.</hi> It is remember <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>what</hi> only, but <hi>how,</hi> not the <hi>matter,</hi> but the <hi>manner;</hi> Remember that. He will keep it, though He die for it; and though He die for it, He will riſe againe <hi>the third Day,</hi> to keepe it to a minute. Pleaſe you, ſee one reaſon yet, why, of all the actions of Chriſt for vs, recorded in the Creede,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12693:18"/>only this action of <hi>riſing,</hi> though of all the moſt difficult, yet it is to be beleeu'd with the <hi>circumstance of time,</hi> and no other; it is to ſhew, that be the doubt, the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, the danger, the improbability, the impoſſibility, in reſpect of the meanes, what it will, yet <hi>whenſoeuer</hi> Hee has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd, He keeps that, aſwell as <hi>whatſoeuer</hi> He has promis'd.</p>
            <p>And, howſoeuer <hi>familiar custome,</hi> has brought both the exerciſes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of godlineſſe, into ſuch <hi>contemptuous neglect,</hi> as there is ſcarce any reuerence to a <hi>diuine preſence,</hi> to be found in <hi>diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice;</hi> Yet <hi>when</hi> you pray, <hi>when</hi> you are baptis'd, <hi>when</hi> you receiue, <hi>when</hi> you heare, <hi>when</hi> you confeſſe, <hi>when</hi> you are abſolu'd, <hi>when</hi> you releeue, <hi>when</hi> you forgiue, <hi>when</hi> you entertaine, defende, or aduance the Prophets: <hi>Dixit?</hi> Hath Hee promis'd any thing at <hi>theſe times? Factum eſt;</hi> it is done at <hi>thoſe times.</hi> Why? Vpon what Article of my Creede is this grounded? Why, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the <hi>third Day.</hi> He that was <hi>cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, dead, buried, ſeal'd vp,</hi> and <hi>watch't in his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12693:18"/>graue,</hi> and in all eyes, it was impoſſible He ſhould keepe either <hi>word or time:</hi> And yet then He kept both, and to the very <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the ſtrickteſt manner; as wee ſay in our Baptiſme, <hi>Doubt you not therefore, but ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beleeue, when</hi> you are baptiz'd, Hee <hi>then</hi> regenerates, <hi>when</hi> you pray together, He is <hi>then</hi> in the mid'ſt, <hi>when</hi> you receiue the Communion; it is <hi>then</hi> his body and bloud, <hi>when</hi> you heare the word, He <hi>then</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>when</hi> you confeſſe your ſinnes, you <hi>then</hi> confeſſe to him, <hi>when</hi> you are abſolu'd by the Keyes, Hee <hi>then</hi> abſolues you, <hi>when</hi> you releeue, He <hi>then</hi> receiues, <hi>when</hi> you <hi>forgiue</hi> your enemies, Hee <hi>then</hi> forgiues, <hi>when</hi> you entertaine, defend, or aduance the Prophets, you <hi>then,</hi> euen <hi>then,</hi> entertaine, defend, and aduance euen Chriſt himſelfe. And this is ſome vertue more, that our <hi>times are certaine,</hi> and <hi>at his appointed times:</hi> let the <hi>meanes</hi> be dead, and all reaſon and probability <hi>buryed and ſeal'd</hi> vp from vs, yet we are <hi>ſure of Him,</hi> Hee is there <hi>then,</hi> and He keepes his time duely. But yet this is not all He has done for our
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12693:19"/>times; we are not yet come to <hi>times full re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude all, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> as I began, and to keep <hi>time</hi> too. <hi>Touch</hi> the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt Ieſus</hi> we muſt, with that <hi>Faith</hi> onely, that <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues only,</hi> and <hi>adores</hi> the myſtery of grace, ſo are we iuſtified in Him, made members of Him. Touch the <hi>Garment</hi> of his works we muſt with that <hi>Faith</hi> only, that does not only beleeue, but <hi>works thorow</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles his loue;</hi> ſo are wee ſanctified in him, and couered with His righteouſnes. Touch the <hi>Hem</hi> of His garment, the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of His workes we muſt, with that <hi>Faith</hi> only, that does not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and worke in groſſe, but is <hi>the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> and <hi>proportion,</hi> faſhioning our conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation to His in heauen, our <hi>time, place, meanes, manners,</hi> to His onely, ſo are wee glorified in Him, with the <hi>glorious liberty of the ſonnes of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to ſhew in ſome ſort this <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>proportion</hi> betwixt Chriſt &amp; vs, S. Paul tels vs,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.23.</note> 1. Cor. 15.23. There <hi>Ordo Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentium,</hi> An <hi>Order of Riſers,</hi> erected by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12693:19"/>Chriſt himſelfe, and himſelfe is the <hi>preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> of that order. Firſt Chriſt, and then they that are Chriſts in order: and this, I dare ſay, is <hi>Gratus ſermo,</hi> an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſaying: For all men deſire to be of this order. It is neither ſcandall to greatones, nor imputation to meaner in Kings Courts, to ſay, wee <hi>courteirs would all verygladly riſe,</hi> and bee inſtall'd in this <hi>order of riſers.</hi> But if you would doe ſo, you know, there is a credit and a Creed to be remembred; To get into this <hi>order,</hi> you muſt follow your <hi>Prince &amp; preſident;</hi> And to keepe order with him, you muſt keepe his <hi>times duly,</hi> his very dayes, and thoſe are but <hi>three dayes</hi> now, &amp; no more; for I haue yet another myſtery to tell you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abbreuiatum faciet Deus opus ſuper terram:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thom. Preſat. in decal.</note> So the olde ones read that place of Eſay, cited by S. Paul, Rom. 9.28. which wee read thus, <hi>Aſhort worke will the Lord make vpon earth:</hi> and this ſhort worke, ſay they, is the worke of our <hi>redemption</hi> from eternall euill,
<note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> with reſtauration into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good. Wherein as God the ſonne, our
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12693:20"/>Lord, <hi>abbreuiated</hi> the <hi>equality with God,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faſhion of <hi>man,</hi> and that <hi>man,</hi> the meaneſt of men, a poore Miniſter and ſeruant, to redeeme the diuiſion between God and man, and make the Higheſt God, and the loweſt man, at one againe: ſo the ſame Lord, &amp; ſeruant, has wrought out and perfected this <hi>redemption,</hi> and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion amongſt men by <hi>abbreuiation</hi> onely, and making ſhort worke in all. <hi>Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, perſons, place, words, time,</hi> all the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, by which, either the kind, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition, content, knowledge, or the actions of men are differenc'd, and diuided, they are all now <hi>abbreuiated</hi> and made ſhorter: we are redeem'd <hi>now</hi> from <hi>distinctions of kindred,</hi> and all <hi>generations</hi> are <hi>abbreuiated</hi> into the <hi>Newbirth</hi> in the lauer of regeneration, wherein wee are all <hi>now</hi> of one <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>blood:</hi> we are redeemed now, from diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of condition, for all <hi>perſons</hi> are <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breuiated</hi> into the Perſon and body of Chriſt, wherein wee are all members <hi>of one Perſon,</hi> of one ſuffering and honour: we are redeem'd <hi>now</hi> from all diſtinctions
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12693:20"/>of <hi>contents;</hi> for all places are <hi>abbreuiated</hi> into the Church and Communion of Saints, wherein, <hi>meum</hi> is <hi>tuum,</hi> and <hi>tuum</hi> is <hi>meum;</hi> Our deſire the ſame becauſe our <hi>poſſeſsion and content</hi> is one and the ſame: we are redeem'd <hi>now</hi> from diſtinction of knowledge, &amp; diuiſion of vnderſtanding; for all wordes are <hi>abbreuiated</hi> into theſe three, faith, hope, and charity: Theſe are all our ſtudy, and the ſtudy of all alike, for the meaſure of all knowledge. Laſtly, we are redeem'd <hi>now</hi> from the <hi>diſtinction of indeuours,</hi> and diuiſion of will and choice in <hi>doing;</hi> for all time, the meaſure of all actions, is <hi>abbreuiated</hi> in theſe three daies of Chriſt, the <hi>Preparation,</hi> the <hi>Sabhath,</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> And as wee haue no <hi>kinred</hi> to deriue to, but the <hi>Newbirth,</hi> no condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of honour, but in the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt,</hi> no content in place, but in the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> no words to ſtudy, but <hi>faith, hope, and charity:</hi> So we haue no <hi>time</hi> to obſerue for the meaſure of all our a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe <hi>three dayes,</hi> and we haue no actions at all, to will, chuſe or doe, but what are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12693:21"/>meaſured and fitted to <hi>theſe three Dayes;</hi> the <hi>Preparation,</hi> the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> the <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion.</hi> Theſe are the meaſure, ſamplar and patterne, to our dayes, or elſe of Chriſts order we cannot be.</p>
            <p>The dayes of our life, muſt be our day of <hi>Preparation,</hi> our Good <hi>Friday,</hi> as was Chriſts, and as it was His, and no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. In it, wee muſt <hi>labour</hi> againſt ſinne and Sathan, as Chriſt did, we muſt <hi>ſuffer</hi> from ſin &amp; Sathan, as Chriſt did, we muſt <hi>die</hi> in conqueſt of ſin &amp; Sathan, as Chriſt did. And now, how like the order? But be not diſmaied; for after this will ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed our <hi>Iewiſh and Typicall Sabbath,</hi> the day of our reſt in the graue, as Chriſt did, in the hands of Chriſt onely, and not of deeath at all, no more then he did. And then will yet follow, the <hi>ſpirituall and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Sabbath,</hi> the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and the day of Lords, the day of reſurrection vnto life, and full enſtallment in this order.</p>
            <p>This the order: Both <hi>habited, armed,</hi> and <hi>tim'd</hi> like your <hi>Preſident</hi> you muſt be; and then, as in other orders, it is a <hi>fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:12693:21"/>as well as an order.
<note place="margin">Auguſt. in 29 Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc ſperate mea membra quod in capite praeceſsit,</hi> ſayes Saint Auguſtine; and t'is the Word &amp; <hi>Motto</hi> of your <hi>order:</hi> What the <hi>Head</hi> enioyes, let the <hi>member expect;</hi> what is gone before in the <hi>Head,</hi> according to his <hi>vertue,</hi> let the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> expect in his <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>condition.</hi> As, let our firſt day bee <hi>troubleſome,</hi> as Chriſts was; yet it ſhall be <hi>ſhort,</hi> and the ſhorteſt of the three, as Chriſts was. Let our ſecond day of death be <hi>longer</hi> by many houres, as Chriſts was; yet it ſhall bee as <hi>long</hi> in reſt, as Chriſts was. Let our third day bee <hi>long</hi> before it come; yet it will come, and come <hi>earely,</hi> as Chriſts did, and when it does come, it ſhall <hi>neuer know euening,</hi> as Chriſts did: And that's a further comfort yet in <hi>this third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time of the <hi>member</hi> of Chriſt, is redeemed and is <hi>abbreuiated</hi> into <hi>three Dayes onely,</hi> and but <hi>two</hi> of thoſe <hi>Dayes</hi> haue <hi>nights</hi> belonging to a'm. <hi>The third Day</hi> has no <hi>night,</hi> but is euer day, as Chriſts was. In theſe <hi>three Dayes</hi> His ſtate, and condition is by ſucceſſion, firſt <hi>trouble</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:12693:22"/>with the Croſſe, then <hi>rest</hi> in death, then <hi>happineſse</hi> in Heauen. Firſt <hi>trouble</hi> with the Croſſe, for which hee has the <hi>Grace of Faith,</hi> both begun, and perfited heere, to lead, and defend him all his <hi>firſt day.</hi> But faith has a <hi>night,</hi> and dies with him and his Croſſe. Then comes his <hi>reſt:</hi> for which hee has the grace <hi>of hope</hi> begunne heere, to aſſiſt faith, but perfited in death, to eſtabliſh him in comfort, all his <hi>ſecond day.</hi> But hope has a <hi>night</hi> too, and leaues him, when hee leaues to reſt in death. Then comes his <hi>happineſſe,</hi> for which he has the <hi>grace of loue,</hi> begunne heere, to make faith and hope actiue, continued in death, to ſweeten hopes reſt, but perfited in eternall life, with God that is loue in <hi>eſſe,</hi> with whom there is no night, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes day without either end or change: And then time is <hi>redeem'd</hi> into eternity.</p>
            <p>And now you, moſt Honourable, and bleſſed order of Riſers, may it pleaſe you, value your order, with the honour and rule of it, as you are <hi>regenerated</hi> in Chriſt, <hi>members</hi> of his body, <hi>Saints</hi> by Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12693:22"/>
               <hi>ſtudents</hi> of faith, hope, and charity, and of <hi>the order</hi> of the Reſurrection to life. The bloud that runnes in your veins, is <hi>Sanguis Dei,</hi> the bloud of God: And then S. Peters <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is your Charter of Priuiledge, againſt all power of death. You die not, when you die, but onely to end your troubles, and ſhew you are of a mortall nature; you ſhall <hi>rest in peace,</hi> as Chriſt did. <hi>Impoſsible</hi> it is, but the <hi>bloud of God</hi> ſhould riſe. But ah the miſery! The ſeruant is not aboue his Lord, the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is not aboue his Maſter, the member is not aboue the <hi>Head.</hi> And riſe we cannot, poſſibly, but as our <hi>Head</hi> did, vpon a <hi>third Day.</hi> And to riſe vpon a <hi>third Day,</hi> it is impoſſible, vnleſſe <hi>two dayes</hi> goe before it. Nay, nor <hi>reſt</hi> can we poſſibly vpon a <hi>ſecond day,</hi> vnleſſe the <hi>firſt day</hi> goe before it. So it is ordered now, and there is no brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it: No skipping to the <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on day,</hi> without both the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration:</hi> No, nor any getting to the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> without wee take our riſe at the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12693:23"/>
               <hi>preparation.</hi> The <hi>riſe</hi> both to <hi>reſt,</hi> and <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> is heere onely. Is there no riſe heere at combat with the croſſe? Why then no reſt in death, and then no happineſſe in the reſurrection. Is there no <hi>fighting faith</hi> with baſe and diſhonourable temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? why then <hi>no resting hope,</hi> and then, <hi>no riſing loue.</hi> Had not Chriſt <hi>reſiſted</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, Hee had not <hi>died</hi> in conqueſt; and had He not <hi>died</hi> ſo, Hee had not <hi>riſen</hi> in triumph and glory. But all this our Prince and Preſident muſt doe, and did for vs, and all this wee muſt doe for him. And if all this wee doe, and in this order; If faith feele a <hi>good Friday,</hi> and haue ſo fought with the Croſſe; as at the houre of death, though faith die, yet hope and loue ſtand conquerours aboue all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Then as ſure as Chriſt <hi>our head,</hi> conquer'd vpon the <hi>preparation,</hi> reſted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and roſe againe vpon the <hi>third day;</hi> ſo ſure ſhall our <hi>hope</hi> reſt ſecure and ſweetly in death, <hi>our ſecond day,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death our <hi>loue</hi> ſhall riſe in triumph vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12693:23"/>
               <hi>the third Day,</hi> to enioy that <hi>happineſſe,</hi> that <hi>faith</hi> fought for heere, <hi>hope</hi> reſted in, in death, and <hi>loue</hi> onely enioyes without <hi>night</hi> or <hi>faile.</hi> To which happineſſe, He bring vs, that, to purchaſe it as deerely as gloriouſly for vs, was crucified, dead, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and roſe againe the <hi>third Day,</hi> Ieſus Chriſt the righteous: To whom, with God the Father, and God the Holy Ghoſt, one true, eternall, euer-liuing, onely wiſe God, be aſcribed, as is moſt due, all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, prayſe, power, glory, dominion and thankeſgiuing, the firſt, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and <hi>third Day,</hi> and for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12693:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> ¶ Printed by IOHN BILL. <hi>M.DC.XXII.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12693:24"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
